<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Jake&#39;s Notes on Basic Finance</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Jake&#39;s Notes on Basic Finance</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.148.1</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 20:03:17 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Credit Card Interest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/credit-card-interest/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 10:10:58 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/credit-card-interest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A brief explainer on what your credit card interest looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;breakdown&#34;&gt;Breakdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit card interest is typically very high. As of 2024, it&amp;rsquo;s around 24% APR (annual percentage rate), which is an annoying way of saying about 2% every month. You can take your credit card’s APR and divide it by 12 to calculate the interest that will accrue on your balance each month. That ‘each month’ aspect of credit card interest makes it easy to fall into debt quickly if you’re not careful. If you bite off more than you can chew, you don’t have much time to fix the situation before the interest adds up. Let’s get into it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tax Brackets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/tax-brackets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 10:10:58 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/tax-brackets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A brief explainer on tax brackets and your paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;breakdown&#34;&gt;Breakdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you&amp;rsquo;re at an all-you-can-eat buffet with different price tiers based on the amount of food you actually consume. The more you eat, the higher the tier you move into, but you only pay that higher price for the food you eat in that tier. In the U.S., tax brackets work similarly: your income is divided into chunks, and each chunk is taxed at a different rate. So, if you earn more, only the extra income in the higher bracket gets taxed at the higher rate, not your entire paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
